<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://unlawfulenrichment.github.io</id>
    <title>Lucien的博客</title>
    <updated>2024-12-11T12:31:04.675Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://unlawfulenrichment.github.io"/>
    <link rel="self" href="https://unlawfulenrichment.github.io/atom.xml"/>
    <subtitle>希望自己刚毅坚卓</subtitle>
    <logo>https://unlawfulenrichment.github.io/images/avatar.png</logo>
    <icon>https://unlawfulenrichment.github.io/favicon.ico</icon>
    <rights>All rights reserved 2024, Lucien的博客</rights>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[行政诉讼律师-文献梳理]]></title>
        <id>https://unlawfulenrichment.github.io/post/xing-zheng-su-song-lu-shi-wen-xian-shu-li/</id>
        <link href="https://unlawfulenrichment.github.io/post/xing-zheng-su-song-lu-shi-wen-xian-shu-li/">
        </link>
        <updated>2024-11-27T08:25:51.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4 id="books">books</h4>
<ul>
<li>Randall Peerenboom, China’s Long March Toward Rule of Law (Cambridge University Press, 2009)</li>
<li>Yuhua Wang, Tying the Autocrat’s Hand: The Rise of the Rule of Law in China (Cambridge University Press, 2015)</li>
<li>Kwai Hang Ng &amp; Xin He, Embedded Courts: Judicial Decision-Making in China (Cambridge University Press, 2017)</li>
<li>Kevin J. O’Brien &amp; Lianjiang Li, Rightful Resistance in Rural China (Cambridge University Press, 2006)</li>
<li>【重要-分析了行政诉讼律师的作用】Givens, J., and John Wagner Givens. Suing Dragons? Taking the Chinese State to Court. Oxford University, UK, 2013.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="chinese-adminitrative-litigation-research">Chinese (adminitrative) litigation research</h4>
<p>Boutcher, S.A. and McCammon, H.J. (2018). Social Movements and Litigation. In The Wiley Blackwell Companion to Social Movements (eds D.A. Snow, S.A. Soule, H. Kriesi and H.J. McCammon). https://doi.org/10.1002/9781119168577.ch17</p>
<ol>
<li>【the performative appearances of chief officials in court】 Chen, T., W. Xu and X. Yu (2024). &quot;Administrative Litigation in China: Assessing the Chief Officials’ Appearance System.&quot; The China Quarterly: 1-21.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><strong>Pragmatism</strong>: Plaintiffs have become more pragmatic in their approach to administrative litigation. They value the opportunity to communicate face-to-face with chief officials, hoping it will help address their grievances.【!】The plaintiffs seems to think that it is the the chief offical who can solve their problem, instead of the courts itself.
<ol>
<li>when officials did appear, it often resulted in more grievances rather than resolving existing ones.
<ol>
<li>Plaintiffs’ Expectations vs. Reality: Plaintiffs had high expectations that meeting with chief officials would lead to the resolution of their grievances. They anticipated that face-to-face interactions would result in favorable outcomes and better compensation, especially in cases like land acquisitions. However, when these expectations were not met, plaintiffs became more agitated and were more likely to appeal or file new suits.</li>
<li>Indifferent and Overconfident Officials: Many chief officials who did appear in court showed indifference or overconfidence, which further frustrated plaintiffs. These officials often remained silent during proceedings, only reading prepared statements, and did not engage actively in the trial process. This lack of engagement was perceived negatively by plaintiffs, who expected more substantial interactions and responses.</li>
<li>Timing and Frequency of Appearances: The timing of officials’ appearances was often tied to annual evaluations rather than the specifics of the cases. Most officials appeared in court at the end of the year to meet performance evaluation criteria, which gave the impression that their participation was a formality rather than a genuine effort to resolve disputes.</li>
<li>Lack of Legal Expertise: Many chief officials lacked legal backgrounds and were cautious about making statements that could be used against them. This cautiousness led to minimal participation, which did not satisfy the plaintiffs’ desire for a thorough and respectful hearing of their concerns.</li>
<li>Mismatch of Expectations: There was a significant mismatch between the pragmatic expectations of plaintiffs and the indifferent or performative actions of the officials. Plaintiffs sought concrete results and resolutions, while officials often viewed their appearance as a procedural requirement, leading to further dissatisfaction and escalation of disputes.</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>This combination of unmet expectations, lack of meaningful engagement, and performative appearances contributed to the reproduction of grievances rather than their resolution.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ol start="2">
<li>Stern, R. E., J. Kim and B. L. Liebman (2024). &quot;Performing Legality: When and Why Chinese Government Leaders Show Up in Court.&quot; Journal of Chinese Political Science: 1-19.</li>
<li>Zhan, C. and S. Qiao (2024). &quot;Workload, legal doctrine, and judicial review in an authoritarian regime: A study of expropriation judgments in China.&quot; International Review of Law and Economics 80: 106232.</li>
<li>何海波 (2024). &quot;走出行政诉讼的“卡夫丁峡谷”——行政争议实质性解决纵论.&quot; 中国法律评论(03): 53-69.<br>
1.</li>
<li>何源 (2024). &quot;过度诉讼及其司法规制.&quot; 法学评论 42(06): 166-181.
<ul>
<li>excessive litigation tends to cluster in major central city courts and specific administrativeareas,disproportionately consuming public resources. Often,these cases stem from core disputes but diverge significantly,ostensibly meeting the statutory acceptance criteria but failing to protect rights, oversee administration,or resolve conflicts.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>
<ul>
<li>统计显示,征收拆迁类行政案件进入实体审理的比例低,实体审理的原告胜诉率低,名义上胜诉的原告获得的实体补偿赔偿少。 面对这一现实,当事人只得退而求其次,他们并不奢望法院的单个裁判便能帮助他们实现“艰难的正义”。在他们眼中，只要能够展现矛盾,就有解决的希望;只要有机会引起领导的关注和忧虑，就能增加谈判的筹码。</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>【联想】Administrative Litigation in China: Assessing the Chief Officials’ Appearance System一文中，当事人对于行政诉讼的期待。</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Baik, J. (2023). &quot;Speaking up: why people dare to sue the government in China.&quot; Journal of Law and Society 50(3): 344-368.</li>
<li>Cao, G., C. Liu and L.-A. Zhou (2023). &quot;Suing the government under weak rule of law: Evidence from administrative litigation reform in China.&quot; Journal of Public Economics 222: 104895.</li>
<li>Guang, S. (2023). &quot;Court–Government Interaction in the Context of Administrative Litigation and Competition Enforcement in China.&quot; China: An International Journal 21(4): 191-211.</li>
<li>Zhang, Y. and Z. Liu (2023). &quot;The Rise of the Chinese Judiciary and Its Limits: Administrative Litigation in the Reform Period.&quot; Available at SSRN 4696197.</li>
<li>Lu, S., X. Zhou, Y. Yao and H. Wang (2022). &quot;Suing the state: relative deprivation and peasants’ resistance in land expropriation in China.&quot; The China Quarterly 251: 798-821.</li>
<li>Mao, W. and S. Qiao (2021). &quot;Legal doctrine and judicial review of eminent domain in China.&quot; Law &amp; Social Inquiry 46(3): 826-859.</li>
<li>Song, W. (2021). Winning Impossible Games?–Empirical Analysis on Administrative Litigation between Overseas Enterprises and Administrative Agencies in China in 2014.</li>
<li>He, X. (2014). &quot;Maintaining stability by law: Protest‐supported housing demolition litigation and social change in China.&quot; Law &amp; Social Inquiry 39(4): 849-873.</li>
<li>Li, J. (2013). &quot;Suing the Leviathan—An Empirical Analysis of the Changing Rate of Administrative Litigation in China.&quot; Journal of Empirical Legal Studies 10(4): 815-846.</li>
<li>Givens, J. W. and A. W. MacDonald (2013). Squeezing the Same Old Stone: Suing the Rural Chinese State and the Shift from Tax Reform to Land Seizures. American Political Science Association 2011 Annual Meeting Paper.<br>
<strong>14. Givens, J. and J. W. Givens (2013). Suing dragons? Taking the Chinese state to court, Oxford University, UK.</strong>
<ul>
<li>the source, risk and impact of interference differs depending on the type of case. Courts actually are strategic actors that resist and submit to the outside pressure depending on a wide variety of circumstances.</li>
<li>【a common picture of administrative litigation】: the use of social connections to find and hire a lawyer, unprofitable lawyer’s fees, a lack of strong legal understanding on the part of the plaintiff, the relative indifference of an administrative organ to being sued, a decision against a plaintiff on valid legal grounds, and a plaintiff more or less satisfied, even with a loss.</li>
<li>【few lawyers specializing in Administrative ligation】</li>
<li>【filing cases】Lubman, Bird in a Cage, 207; O’Brien and Li, “Suing the Local State,” 2005, 35–6; Peerenboom, China’s Long March, 420, 440.
<ul>
<li>internal orders forbid courts to accept suits on sensitive matters.</li>
<li>Law firms may be similarly warned not to accept certain kinds of cases</li>
<li>the filing divisions are usually more cautious about administrative cases.</li>
<li>Guanxi may not affect  the outcome of the case, but affect the convenience of handling the case.(131)</li>
<li>a retired court judge: getting cases accepted is not as hard as people think,  but the lawyers are not professional with the administrative litigation law.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>【Q】What are the types and motivations of lawyers involved in administrative litigation?
<ul>
<li>【2 types of lawyers take the vast majority of administrative<br>
cases.】several roles mentioned in the essays: (1)lawyers working throuth the legal system, not the outside of it, even some cause-lawyers; (2) contentious extra-legal activities; (3) the most successful administrative litigators
<ul>
<li><strong>1 political embedded lawyers</strong>——the author attributes their motivation to a sense of justice.【?】
<ul>
<li>Politically embedded lawyers are typically very experienced, financially comfortable, and well respected. They have all the markers of upstanding citizens</li>
<li>【political embeddedness of administrative limitation lawyer 】In part, this is because the most prolific and successful administrative litigators are politically embedded lawyers, insiders who challenge the state in court but eschew themost radical cases and tactics (Chapter Four).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>on the one hands, the lawyers with connections to the state are more likeky to get their cases accepted by court, but they would also aviod severe actions and moderate their bahaviors.</li>
<li>【质疑作者观察？行政诉讼代理政府更多更接受原告？】the author finds that the most important variable for determining how likely a lawyer is to take a case against the state is how likely that lawyer is to represent the state in a different case.</li>
<li>【weak influence of GUANXI in administrative litigation“connections (关系) are probably least important in administrative cases because even if you had good connections with the government, it is the government that you are suing“（192）</li>
<li>being hierd by local government make the lawyers more experience about the government, which may give them more confident to take sensitive cases. <strong>How these guanxi really be used remain unclear for the author.</strong></li>
<li>【质疑作者观察？sue the neighbor department is reasonable for the lawyers?】the author observes that the most of lawyers are willing to defend both sides, and willing to provide legal consult to some bureau while sue the other of the same government or the same department in other jurisdiction.——they show some kinds of duality about their political position.</li>
<li>One frequent administrative litigator (usually on the side of the state) said that <strong>he was not willing to represent the government when he thinks they are completely wrong</strong>. “I will tell them how to resolve it but I will not represent them.” If you “…can’t win and don’t have any argument to make, I don’t want to help the government screw someone, it isn’t honest.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>type 2 reluctant lawyer.——a friend in need or professional responsibility.
<ul>
<li>【which side？】The questionof which side lawyers are on is obviously vital for understanding their role in administrative litigation and their impact on the Chinese state.</li>
<li>【financial incentives and fees】many interiewees says the administrative cases are unprofitable.(1)fee in administrative cases lower than ip, contract and other civil cases, but still more higher than those for labour or family cases. (2)fees for administrative cases increase faster than other cases.</li>
<li>【Input-output is disproportionate】the data from lawyer annual review reveals that the fee for administrative cases is modest, but it is more time-consuming and difficult than other civil cases.</li>
<li>【sensitive cases】not accepted by courts and refuse on appeal. law firms may receive notices that certain categories of cases wil not be accepted.
<ul>
<li>【Q】the state may prevent the criminal defense lawyer to participate in criminal procedure——vs the state refuse to accept the sensitive administrative cases. will the different structure between the two types of cases result in different risk? the administrative case suffer low risk than criminal cases?</li>
<li>【A from the author is yes】Lawyers, especially those with close connections to the state, may be told in private by apologetic judges that political pressure will not allow them to accept this case or to find in favour of the plaintiff. An official who can pressure courts to find in his favour or reject a case against him has no need to retaliate against plaintiffs or their lawyers. While this proves a disappointing outcome for plaintiffs, it may prove in the long run to be a positive for China’s legal system as it reduces the risk to lawyers.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>【role identity-work through the legal system】nearly all of my informants saw themselves primarily as lawyers whose role is to work through the legal system, not outside it.</li>
<li>They are a conservative force of reform primarily working towards improving rule of law and government accountability rather than democracy or other liberal goals. They may be doing as much, or more, to support China’s authoritarian regime as to challenge it, even as they soften its rough edges.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>effective strategies to challenge the state
<ul>
<li>conclusion: The fact that the very same lawyers who represent the state, sue the state, suggests that this is largely a process in which certain actors areinvited into the elite circle of power holders, rather than one in which power is extended out towards the masses.</li>
<li>the strategies are not only helpful to deal with the sensitive case, but also useful in ordinary cases to maintain the good relationship with the state.
<ul>
<li><strong>Levelling up and over</strong>_the most basic strategy lawyers use in administrative litigation.——not issue the written ruling over ducument to prevent the plaintiff from appealing to the higher court.</li>
<li>political connections: experience and deterrent effect to political coersion.</li>
<li>the shotgun strategy:  when it is unclear which department of the local government is the proper target of litigation since officials often try to obscure their identitied and affiliations when engaged in legally dubious activities.
<ul>
<li>2 advantages:(1)name the officials in litigation;(2)force the various department to suss out which organ is at fault or at least to pick a scapegoat.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>the cross jurisdicional strategy
<ul>
<li>Despite being under the same prefectural government, lawyers from neighboring counties may send each other cases that they feel are more sensitive</li>
<li>geographic separation and distance also protect the lawyers.</li>
<li>the lawyers from higher level jurisdictions, such as from provincial capital, direct-control municipalities, are likely to be better educated, speak more standard Chinese and have stronger legal expertise than local officials. They also tend to be well respected by judges.
<ul>
<li>because the local government do not know the background of the outside lawyers, may not risk treating a lawyer too aggressively or badly for fear that he or she might have connections to high ranking people in his or her home city, especially Beijing.</li>
<li>when facing the expertised lawyer from big citied, the government finds it is increasingly important to hire a private lawyer(perhaps from local law firms) to instead letting the law institution officials to represent in the cases.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>limitation:(1) local goverment turn to retaliate the lawyers though third party or individuals hiding their official status.(2) it is not work well in Beijing or Shanghai.(3) without consideration about the consequece and harm to the plaintiff and local law firms, deterioate the litigation environment.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>media strategy</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>winning may be not the best result for the client.Non-litigated outcomes may be able to provide an opportunity for success even when “the court would not accept the case.【L的自身观察】negotiation may help the court to build its own authority and confident withe the local governent, which may benefit the subsequent cases.</li>
<li>counterstrategies:
<ul>
<li>retaliation\using third party</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Li, J. (2012). Suing the State: A Study of Administrative Litigation at the Provincial Level in China, Northwestern University.</li>
<li>Haibo, H. (2010). &quot;Litigations without a ruling: The predicament of administrative law in China.&quot; Tsinghua China L. Rev. 3: 257.</li>
<li>HE, X. F. (2009). Administrative law as a mechanism for political control in contemporary China. Building constitutionalism in China, Palgrave Macmillan.</li>
<li>O'Brien, K. J. and L. Li (2004). &quot;Suing the local state: administrative litigation in rural China.&quot; The China Journal(51): 75-96.
<ol>
<li>select the extreme cases?</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Pei, M. (1997). &quot;Citizens v. mandarins: administrative litigation in China.&quot; The China Quarterly 152: 832-862.
<ol>
<li>empirical analyisis and also thought to representativeness and generalizability.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>贺欣 (2012). &quot;法院推动的司法创新实践及其意涵——以 T 市中级人民法院的行政诉讼为例.&quot; 法学家(5): 1.</li>
<li>贺欣 (2008). &quot;为什么法院不接受外嫁女纠纷——司法过程中的法律、权力和政治.&quot; 法律和社会科学 3(00): 66-97+66.</li>
<li>贺欣 (2005). &quot;作为政治控制机制之一的行政法——当代中国行政法的政治学解读.&quot; 法哲学与法社会学论丛 8(00): 207-226+340.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="layer">Layer</h3>
<h2 id="政府法律顾问-公职律师-政府律师-政府法制机构人员-政府常法概念的区别">政府法律顾问、公职律师、政府律师、政府法制机构人员、政府常法概念的区别</h2>
<p>司法部《关于律师担任政府法律顾问的若干规定》（1989）<br>
《深圳市人民政府法律顾问工作规则》</p>
<ul>
<li>顾问队伍以法制机构工作人员为主体、吸收专家和律师参加<br>
《广东省政府法律顾问工作规定》<br>
公职律师——具有律师资格，，为各级党委、政府、事业单位、人民团体提供法律服务的国家公职人员<br>
政府律师——微观业务：参与各级党委、事业单位、人民团体及政府的微观法律事务，如代理行政复议、行政诉讼、民事诉讼等——消防员<br>
政府法顾——宏观业务：参与政府宏观法律事务，如参与政府立法、重大行政决策等——智囊团和守门员</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="乡村律师土律师">乡村律师“土律师”</h2>
<ul>
<li>
<p>汪庆华《政治中的司法：中国行政诉讼的法律社会学考察》 第四章</p>
<ul>
<li>山东太谷县农民律师周广立十年的行政诉讼经历
<ul>
<li>周是如何进入行政诉讼领域的？——《行政诉讼法》五周年纪念日的法院宣传下，周以公民代理的身份进入法院。</li>
<li>作者注意到了周的【律师经历阶段】，阶段划分参见应星：《“迎法入乡”与“接近正义”————对中国乡村“赤脚律师”的个案研究》
<ul>
<li>初起阶段：主要涉及本地乡政府，逐渐获得农民认可，与本地政府关系紧张。</li>
<li>争议阶段：周广立现象得到媒体关系，影响逐渐扩大上升。
<ul>
<li>阳谷县政府批判周广立现象。</li>
<li>2000年新华社关于周广立现象的上内参。省市委主要领导批示。同年市县组成调查组，对周广立现象进行了深入调查。调查组最后的结论是：<strong>“周广立现象 ”对社会有利,受到了群众的信任和欢迎；同时,对这一现象要加以正确对待和引导,并加以规范。</strong></li>
<li>Q：不同层级政府的态度？以及政府系统对于——信访——vs——行政诉讼的不同态度，这种态度是理性的吗？（出于政治绩效、考核以及压力的不同？还是有一定的观念影响，上访意味着敌对而诉讼不是？）</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>相对自主阶段：市县联合调查组的调查报告含糊地提出了要引导 “周广立现象 ”,但并没有说如何引导。由于调查报告的基调是大体肯定的,所以,县乡政府从此不再敢对周广立施加压力了。
<ul>
<li>Q：为什么没有后续引导？为什么县乡政府之后又开始阻碍了？（因为内参作用耗散？省委领导的离开？县乡主政者的调动？周广立影响的不断升级？代理了一些格外敏感触及红线的案子？）</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>收缩阶段：应星认为，随着时间的流逝,市县联合调查报告给他定性的 “保护伞 ”作用也开始消褪。——为什么会耗散？</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>土律师出现的原因：具有正式身份的法律人无法充分回应乡土社会行政纠纷的需求
<ul>
<li>Q：为什么无法回应？乡土社会行政纠纷的需求是什么？有什么特殊性？</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>谱系分析：土律师在行政诉讼法律人谱系中位置
<ul>
<li>Q：谱系是一个纯粹形式上的概念分析工具？分析谱系有什么作用？</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>the tension between citizen individualism （公民个体主义）and governance through law（法律治理化）</li>
<li>土律师的复杂面向：官民沟通中介——与——送法下乡</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>应星：《“迎法入乡”与“接近正义”————对中国乡村“赤脚律师”的个案研究》</p>
<ul>
<li>国家法的主体性是否可以被本土资源所扭转？什么叫做国家法的主体性？普适的法律概念是否可能被破解为地方性知识的问题。</li>
<li>“送法下乡”——农民被动、他者的视角；而“迎法下乡”——农民主动地寻求法律？</li>
<li>“基层”作为法律服务市场：律师、法律服务工作者、公民代理三种群体的生态位
<ul>
<li>公民代理制度已经被诉讼法限制，但它带来的思考是什么？</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>应星认为：个人性格和遭遇（而非经济回报、抽象理念追求）是赤脚律师进入法律职业的原因。</li>
<li>赤脚律师的扩散效应：法律由农民自发地在乡间传播的现象。</li>
<li>赤脚律师的市场：中国法律市场在2008年的问题，不够、不敢（法律服务所与政府的历史勾连，使得法律服务所对行政诉讼业务的态度消极）、不廉、不亲（纯粹业务委托关系）
<ul>
<li>周广立如何谋生？当事人的人情和回礼，以及其他经济案件的报酬。立足于情而非利的动机更能够为农民所接受。<strong># 应星“法律市场的 “图利 ”原则更换为法律服务的 “互惠 ”原则,就是乡村社会自我保护运动的一部分。”</strong></li>
<li>周广立的市场如何拓展？个别案件的轰动效应&amp;地方乃至全国媒体的报道</li>
<li>关系：
<ul>
<li>与法院特别是行政庭的复杂关系</li>
<li>gatekeeper作用——“小案好办,大案没法办 ”——自主筛选小案、大案。——这一观察和在明律师事务所的律师对于当事人希望撤销征收项目的诉求明确拒绝类似。
<ul>
<li>县法院给县政府的请示——案件背后复杂的考量。</li>
<li>复杂关系网：（1）县法院、县委、县政法委、县政府、各乡政府、中院；（2）类似遭遇的农民示范效应。</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>与政府的关系
<ul>
<li>模范农民、拒绝上访、与农民活动家保持距离、婉拒外国学者访谈、避免代理本地案件、与其他农民律师形成异地交叉代理的合作关系。</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>与农民的关系：熟人社会的人情交往</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Q：2007年，应星和汪观察到“土律师”不同于“职业律师”、“黑心律师”的独特身份、动机和收费方式。现在，土律师是否还有生存空间？为什么？国家为何需要限制公民代理？公民代理中黑律师和“赤脚律师”的区别是什么？赤脚律师的动机和信念是什么？他们的市场何在，这些市场在后来发生了什么变化？</strong><br>
Q：行政法领域的职业者的信念感是否更强？如果是，它是否影响了行政法领域的法律实践？</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="调解律师">调解律师</h2>
<ul>
<li>张永华. “诉源治理”视角下律师权威的塑造[J]. 河北法学, 2023, 41 (05): 135-153.
<ul>
<li>本文问题：诉源治理中律师通过调解基层社会纠纷参与基础社会治理，Q：律师调解的权威是如何获得的？它的行使又存在哪些障碍？
<ul>
<li>【时代背景】中国社会格局的转型，导致了人民调解的衰落，人们日益诉诸正式纠纷解决途径。</li>
<li>【制度背景】多元纠纷解决机制建设</li>
<li>【定义】<a href="http://gongbao.court.gov.cn/Details/aad777e0a08dbb4df4192df26c706e.html">律师调解是指律师、依法成立的律师调解工作室或者律师调解中心作为中立第三方主持调解，协助纠纷各方当事人通过自愿协商达成协议解决争议的活动。</a></li>
<li>【领域】各类民商事纠纷，以及刑事诉讼附带民事诉讼的民事部分——<strong>不包括行政诉讼</strong></li>
<li>【场所】人民法院、公共服务中心、律师协会以及律师事务所设立</li>
<li>【费用】
<ul>
<li>律师事务所-有偿和低价的原则向双方当事人收取调解费</li>
<li>公共法律服务中心（站）、律师协会设立的律师调解中心，由司法行政机关、律师协会通过政府采购服务的方式解决经费。律师调解员调解法律援助案件的经费，由法律援助机构通过政府采购服务渠道予以解决。</li>
<li>人民法院设立律师调解工作室的，由政府采购服务渠道解决调解经费，并纳入人民法院专项预算。</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>律师和“诉源治理”为什么有关系？律师为何在现实承担起了“诉源治理”的任务？</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="authoritarian-legality">authoritarian legality</h4>
<p>these authoritarian states have a legal system with duality——“law matters<br>
sometimes, but not always”. The courts and other state organs are still pursuing the public good when it will not weaken political control.</p>
<ul>
<li>【main debate】whether the dual legal system will bolster or undermine the political stability?</li>
<li>【privious reseach】usually focus on the political control over the <strong>courts</strong> not the <strong>lawyers</strong>.</li>
<li>Solomon, Peter H. “Authoritarian Legality and Informal Practices: Judges, Lawyers and the State in Russia and China.” Communist and Post-Communist Studies 43, no. 4 (2010): 351–62;“Law and Courts in Authoritarian States.” International Encyclopedia of the Social &amp; Behavioral Sciences (2015): 427–34.</li>
<li>Moustafa, Tamir, and Tom Ginsburg. “Introduction: The Functions of Courts in Authoritarian Politics.” In Rule by Law: The Politics of Courts in Authoritarian Regimes. Edited by Tom Ginsburg and Tamir Moustafa, 1–22. New York: Cambridge University Press, 2008.</li>
<li>Moustafa, Tamir. “Law and Courts in Authoritarian Regimes.” Annual Review of Law and Social Science 10, no. 1 (2014): 281–99.</li>
<li>Tom Ginsburg“Administrative Law and Judicial Control of Agents in Authoritarian Regimes”</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="legal-profession-research-in-authoritarian-country">legal profession research in authoritarian country</h4>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Stern, Rachel E., and Lawrence J. Liu. “The Good Lawyer: State-Led Professional Socialization in Contemporary China.” Law &amp; Social Inquiry 45.1 (2020): 226–248. Web.</p>
<ul>
<li>how authoritarian states like China define and communicate notions of appropriate work conduct and professional excellence to lawyers.</li>
<li>two organization have the direct responsibility for overseeing<br>
the bar: <strong>the ministry of justice and the all china lawyer association.</strong></li>
<li>three main channels to signal the state's expectations to the legal professions——
<ul>
<li>bar exam: the politicization of the Chinese bar exam</li>
<li>administrative rules《律师执业管理办法》、《律师事务所管理办法》
<ul>
<li>only courteous, by-the-book courtroom advocacy is permitted.</li>
<li>the newly revised Administrative Measure requires to establich the part committees in law firms.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>state-sanctioned national outstanding lawyer award.
<ul>
<li>male lawyers with close ties to the government: working advising the government, providing individual legal aid, and bridging the government and the governed.</li>
<li>certain types consistently wins the award: : a well-educated man working in private practice who holds a leadership position in the ACLA or his local bar association.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>【research method】interviews, government documents, and a database of bar exam questions and award recipients.
<ul>
<li><strong>diachronic method</strong>: analyze the evolution of the bar exam and the changes of the regulate rules.</li>
<li>【arenasof professionalism】 key sites where the Chinese authorities detail their vision of the proper role of lawyers in society.</li>
<li><strong>【legal professionalism】not an unitary set of values, but consists of multiple visions of what constitutes proper behavior by lawyers.</strong>
<ul>
<li>refrence: Nelson, Robert L., and David M. Trubek. “Arenas of Professionalism: The Professional Ideologies of Lawyers in Context.” In Lawyers’ Ideals/Lawyers’ Practices: Transformations in the American Legal<br>
Profession. Edited by Robert L. Nelson, David M. Trubek, and Rayman L. Solomon, 177–214. Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 1992.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>【legal activism under authoritarianism】</strong>“依法抗争”</li>
<li>【the state's ideology of a good lawer】includes <strong>a positive,affirmative vision of political participation</strong>. Lawyers are encouraged<br>
to be partners in governance by serving as government advisors, providing public goods through legal aid, and <strong>easing communication between officials and the public.</strong></li>
<li>the attitude of the outstanding lawyers: express negative attitude towards the lawyer activists. the elite lawyers believe that the legal reform is a step-by-step process.——【two key elements】optimistic and patience.</li>
<li>criminal defense lawyers: more working experience is colleated with political liberal altitude.(Sida Liu and Terence Halliday)</li>
<li>【Background】the emergence of a private bar turn the lawyer from civil servants to legal activists. And the the ministry of justive and local justice bureau tried to tighten the political control.</li>
<li>【 research innovation】political control also includes professional socialization. Except the coersion and detterence, the state also use channels to signal the state's expectations to the legal professions.</li>
<li>【anticipation】facing the clearer prescription of lawyers'behaviors, the elite lawyers are more optimistic about the political development.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>刘思达：《割据的逻辑》</p>
<ul>
<li>中国的法制建设一直伴随着国家与其试图发展的市场经济的结构性变化，而这一法律、国家与市场之间独特的并置关系（juxtaposition）在改革开放时期催生了一个高度割据的法律服务市场。</li>
<li>个人法律服务领域：律师、基层法律工作者、法律咨询机构、黑律师、土律师的竞争</li>
<li>企业法律服务领域：外国律师、企业法律顾问、专利代理人、商标代理人和公证员</li>
<li>律师市场地位的不稳固根源在于政府管理规范体制的高度割据</li>
<li>【研究问题】为什么中国三十年的法制建设产生了一个如此割据的法律服务市场？为什么律师在这个市场上四面受敌？而这些包括市场、国家和职业在内的割据的社会结构又是通过怎样的社会过程产生和演变的？</li>
<li>【理论】芝加哥学派的生态分析传统——本研究的法律职业与国家的生态理论——社会结构分化和整合的基本过程。
<ul>
<li>社会学的生态理论</li>
<li>法律职业与国家的生态理论：互动是社会存在的基础——boundary-work&amp;exchange
<ul>
<li>职业社会学：Abbott: jurisdictional conflict——处于同一工作领域的职业视为一个通过“管辖权冲突”而发展的互动系统，各个职业并不单独经历所谓的“职业化”过程，而是共同构成了一个相互依赖的生态系统，通过彼此之间的互动而发展。</li>
<li>endogeneity内生性：来自系统外部（例如国家、公众等）的影响只是生态互动过程的消极条件、homogeneity同质性：生态系统中的行为主体都属于同一个社会学类别——生态分析模型的固有本体论假设</li>
<li>质疑上述本体论假设，用开放性和异质性的生态分析模型分析中国的法律服务市场中职业与政治行为主体之间的关系。</li>
<li>律师试图与其他竞争者自我区分，而其他竞争者则试图让自己与律师更加相似。中国律师在市场上的定界过程不成功的原因，恰恰在于他们与国家之间的交换在许多时候不如其竞争者更强或更稳定。<strong>中国法律服务市场的割据主要是由其国家管理体制结构的割据所产生的。</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>【<strong>排除其他竞争理论</strong>】结构功能理论：高度割据的市场结构是由这些法律职业所服务的客户类型的高度分化所导致——客户需求如何塑造了法律系统的结构；在中国法律服务市场的各个领域，即使当客户类型基本相同时​，还是有多个职业群体在为类似的工作而相互竞争，客户很难分析这些职业，很难说客户需求就是市场社会结构的主要决定因素。<strong>评估功能理论解释力的关键问题并不是客户结构的分化程度如何，而是客户需求如何塑造了法律系统的结构。</strong></li>
<li>【Q】：作者分析的是二十年之前的法律服务市场，现在它遵循割据的逻辑吗？行政诉讼本身的需求差异，是否塑造了律师内部的分化？</li>
<li>中国法律服务市场的五个空间领域：边疆、战场、高端、后院和雷区</li>
<li>具体研究方法：半结构和开放性访谈，辅之以历史文献-发展史；网络民族志-法律执业者关于其市场竞争与国家规范的公共话语</li>
<li>【Q】:首先需要通过访谈了解到中国行政诉讼不同地域的差异，然后选取访谈和观察地点；其次，同样可以运用网络民族志的方法来观察律师向当事人展现何种行政诉讼制度和策略。</li>
<li>边疆 农村的纠纷解决与职业系统
<ul>
<li>甘肃老农的计划生育行政纠纷——国办律师事务所的消极态度——建议其上访而非起诉，在这位律师看来在县法院告乡政府可能不受理，其次他本身不愿意承办起诉乡政府的行政案件。
<ul>
<li>【Q】目前基层的律师事务所数量得以改善，但他们对于行政诉讼的态度是否发生了改变？——基层政府对于代理行政诉讼的律师施加了怎样的压力？这一情况和刑事诉讼相同吗？假设：行政诉讼异地代理的情况更多，那么异地代理本身对行政诉讼产生了怎样的影响？</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>战场 律师与基层法律服务
<ul>
<li>【Q】我注意到：一个非常著名的行政法律师曾经将自己和征拆律师相区别，认为他们并不是”搞行政法的“，”他们的方式我们不搞，我们不乱来“等等。
<ul>
<li>中国的城市化进程和过去的征拆业务催生了大量的行政诉讼需求——但为什么会出现征拆律师这一独特的业务模式？——我的假设（1）原告的激进诉求&amp;原告的规模与利益同质性、（2）当地政府软硬兼施的策略也催生了律师需要同样采用正式诉讼和非正式的模式；（3）行政诉讼不能风险代理，只能事先收费；（4）行政诉讼胜诉的非规范逻辑与不可控性——降低了对于律师能力的要求。<strong>——行政诉讼的程序空转是政治嵌入的具体表现，并且从审判渗透进了代理环节。</strong></li>
<li>比较有趣的是，似乎自诩正规的行政诉讼律师其实很多时候，强调的不是规范意义上的行政法律技能？而是一种应对现实中的行政诉讼的策略。</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>后院 企业与政府机关的法制化
<ul>
<li>2002年起，司法部发起了“公司律师”和“公职律师”的试点工作，其目的恰恰在于加强对企业和政府机关法律工作的控制，但这一改革措施受到了来自国资委和国务院法制办的强大阻力。</li>
<li>Q：这一分离现今还存在吗？各级政府法制办公室为什么取消？有怎样的影响？</li>
<li>法律顾问——并非职业和客户的关系，而是一种公共服务的关系，二者关系不平衡。法制办对公职律师改革的不友好态度。</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>雷区 律师与刑事司法系统
<ul>
<li>刑辩律师的生存策略：【合作、律协、媒体】对于那些涉及社会稳定或者职务犯罪等敏感问题的案件，地方律协或律师事务所会建议两位律师共同合作，以降低困难并彼此保护。</li>
<li>全国律协现在对于律师保护发挥了怎样的角色？是否还如刘思达提到的积极营救陷入伪证罪的律师？</li>
<li>【与国家机关的政治嵌入性】
<ul>
<li>面对巨大的困难和人身危险，我国的大多数律师在从刑事案件中积累了一定声誉之后都会逐渐将工作重点转向民商事案件。</li>
<li>绝大多数坚持办理刑事案件且比较成功的律师都是和公检法机关具有紧密关联的——该现象被麦宜生称为**“政治嵌入性”**​（politicalembeddedness, Michelson, 2007）​。</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>嵌入性：
<ul>
<li>在公检法的工作经验、级别越高优势越大——依法执业，不超出自己的势力范围</li>
<li>法学教育使得兼职律师刑法或者刑诉法教授在律师工作中获得了巨大优势</li>
<li>【本地律师的优势】即使是许多全国知名的刑事辩护律师也会建议外地的当事人在侦查和审查起诉阶段聘请当地律师，因为在这两个阶段里，本地的关系是最为重要的。</li>
<li>【Q】案件同样都受到地方干预和政治影响，为什么刑辩律师建议当事人在侦察和审查起诉阶段聘请当地律师？<strong>同样的逻辑是否适用于行政诉讼律师？</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>Liu, Sida. “Lawyers in Authoritarian Regimes.” Oxford Bibliographies, 2019. doi:10.1093/OBO/9780199756223-0276.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Liu, Sida, and Terence C. Halliday. &quot;Political liberalism and political embeddedness: understanding politics in the work of Chinese criminal defense lawyers.&quot; Law &amp; Society Review 45.4 (2011): 831-865.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Liu, Sida, and Terence C. Halliday. Criminal defense in China: The politics of lawyers at work. Cambridge University Press, 2016.<br>
Juan, Wang, and L. I. U. Sida. &quot;Ordering power under the party: A relational approach to law and politics in China.&quot; Asian Journal of Law and Society 6.1 (2019): 1-18.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Fu, Hualing, and Richard Cullen. “Weiquan (Rights Protection) Lawyering in an Authoritarian State: Building a Culture of Public-Interest Lawyering.” The China Journal, no. 59, 2008, pp. 111–27. JSTOR, http://www.jstor.org/stable/20066382. Accessed 8 Dec. 2024.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Tam, Waikeung. Legal Mobilization under Authoritarianism: The Case of Post-Colonial Hong Kong. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2012. Print. Cambridge Studies in Law and Society.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>McMorrow, Judith A. and Liu, Sida and van Rooij, Benjamin and van Rooij, Benjamin, Lawyer Discipline in an Authoritarian Regime: Empirical Insights from Zhejiang Province, China (June 22, 2017). Georgetown Journal of Legal Ethics, Vol. 30, No. 2, 2017, Boston College Law School Legal Studies Research Paper No. 458, UC Irvine School of Law Research Paper No. 2017-35, Available at SSRN: https://ssrn.com/abstract=2991264</p>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[近期泛读文献]]></title>
        <id>https://unlawfulenrichment.github.io/post/jin-qi-fan-du-wen-xian/</id>
        <link href="https://unlawfulenrichment.github.io/post/jin-qi-fan-du-wen-xian/">
        </link>
        <updated>2024-11-20T12:02:51.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="宪法">宪法</h1>
<h4 id="mazzone-jason-and-tecimer-cem-interconstitutionalism-january-30-2022-university-of-illinois-college-of-law-legal-studies-research-paper-no-22-24">Mazzone, Jason and Tecimer, Cem, Interconstitutionalism (January 30, 2022). University of Illinois College of Law Legal Studies Research Paper No. 22-24.</h4>
<ul>
<li>Available at SSRN: https://ssrn.com/abstract=4021506 or http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.4021506</li>
<li>在论文中，<strong>跨宪法主义（Interconstitutionalism）</strong> 的功能主要包括利用先前的宪法来解释和适用现行宪法。这种解释实践广泛存在，并突出了过去与现在治理章程之间的连续性。跨宪法主义通过保留过往宪法的原则、解释和判例，确保表面上已经废除的宪法仍然对现行法律框架产生影响。</li>
<li>主要功能总结：
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>治理的连续性</strong>：跨宪法主义避免了与历史治理结构的完全断裂。例如，美国宪法在债务义务和条约承认等方面，仍受到《邦联条例》的影响。</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>司法参考</strong>：法院利用跨宪法主义保持法律原则的一致性，通过参考过去宪法来理解当前章程中类似的条款，例如在 <em>McCulloch v. Maryland</em> 案中。</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>增强宪法的合法性</strong>：通过连接过去和现在的法律框架，跨宪法主义强调了现行章程的合法性，使其成为持续发展的宪法叙事的一部分，而不是独立的文件。</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>支持主权与自治</strong>：这一实践提出了关于自我治理程度的问题，因为过去几代人设定的原则仍然在当代治理中发挥作用。这在州宪法和外国宪法中尤为明显，司法机构会分析历史与现代背景之间的连续性。</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>在国际背景中的应用</strong>：跨宪法主义的影响范围遍及全球，例如德国《基本法》纳入了魏玛宪法的特定条款，以确保法律和文化的连续性。</p>
</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="行政法">行政法</h1>
<h3 id="诉讼研究">诉讼研究</h3>
<h4 id="briker-gregory-the-anatomy-of-social-movement-litigation-may-31-2023-yale-law-journal-vol-132-no-7-2023">Briker, Gregory, The Anatomy of Social Movement Litigation (May 31, 2023). Yale Law Journal, Vol. 132, No. 7, 2023,</h4>
<ul>
<li>Available at SSRN: https://ssrn.com/abstract=4483175</li>
<li>Abstract：<br>
-【学术脉络】 Scholars of legal mobilization have addressed how litigation can shape social movements through its indirect effects, as going to court can <strong>unite, mobilize, or legitimize activists and their opponents.</strong> 但以往研究将诉讼作为一个整体，而忽略了其中的不同的程序。
<ul>
<li>this Note attends to the process of litigation in all its complexity, arguing that particular elements of litigation - namely claiming（起诉）, discovery（证据开示）, and record building（记录） - are critical sources of indirect effects.</li>
<li>This Note further argues that while such elements offer activists distinctive opportunities to <strong>draw extralegal benefits from legal action</strong>,</li>
<li>By constructing a new approach to legal mobilization that** highlights the centrality of procedure**, this Note challenges the terms of the debate over the utility of courts to social movements.
<ul>
<li>主张：这涉及活动家及其律师在提起诉讼时选择的具体法律主张。主张的选择可以以某种方式框定不满，使活动家团结起来，激发集体行动，并为运动提供明确的叙述。程序规则，如那些管理主张聚合和诉讼标准的规则，影响哪些主张被视为可行以及它们如何被呈现。</li>
<li>证据开示：证据开示过程允许诉讼当事人获取文件、进行证词记录和收集证据。超越具体案件的作用，证据开示可以挖掘出能够动员公众舆论、揭露不法行为并支持更广泛宣传努力的信息。管理证据开示的程序规则，如可以请求的范围和披露的时间，决定了其作为社会运动工具的有效性。</li>
<li>记录建立：通过诉讼过程创建司法记录，允许活动家在正式的法律背景下记录他们的经历和验证他们的不满。这一记录可以用于进一步的政治行动和运动，提供支持运动目标的书面证据。程序规范和规则决定了如何建立这一记录以及如何在未来的宣传中使用。</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>相关案件：
<ul>
<li>East Ramapo Central School District Voting-Rights Case:
<ul>
<li>This case study examines activists in East Ramapo, New York, who filed a federal vote-dilution lawsuit against the district.The activists knew that a judicial decree in their favor would have limited direct impact due to systemic issues but pursued litigation for its indirect effects, such as drawing attention to their grievances, mobilizing supporters, and challenging the existing power dynamics.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>NAACP and School Desegregation:
<ul>
<li>The NAACP shifted its litigation strategy in the 1940s from material inequities in education to attacking segregation itself, framing it as inherently unequal under the Equal Protection Clause.This shift had significant political and cultural ramifications, uniting activists and reframing public debates about civil rights.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Kelo v. City of New London:
<ul>
<li>A case challenging the use of eminent domain for private redevelopment projects. Initially, plaintiffs raised claims under the Takings Clause, Equal Protection Clause, and Due Process Clause but ultimately focused on the Takings Clause on appeal. Although the plaintiffs lost, the case catalyzed public outrage and legislative reforms in many states to limit eminent domain powers, demonstrating how procedural decisions influenced broader mobilization.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Cipollone v. Liggett Group (Tobacco Litigation):
<ul>
<li>A smoker, Rose Cipollone, sued cigarette companies, alleging they concealed health risks. While the case did not result in direct victory, discovery during litigation uncovered internal documents that mobilized public opinion against the tobacco industry and fueled subsequent legislative and legal actions.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Brown v. Board of Education:
<ul>
<li>Although the decision initially led to little desegregation in schools, it inspired civil rights activists, attracted media attention, and framed the national debate on racial equality, showing the broader effects of litigation beyond its immediate legal outcomes.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Keywords: Social movements, litigation, procedure, legal mobilization</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="politicised-legal-discourse-and-judicial-accommodation-of-petitioners-in-chinese-courts-yuqing-feng-and-qing-xu">Politicised Legal Discourse and Judicial Accommodation of Petitioners in Chinese Courts Yuqing Feng and Qing Xu</h4>
<ul>
<li>上访者被吸纳到常规的法律程序之中，法官竭力将维稳和法治话语统一在一起。而对于这一秩序的反抗被认为是为违法甚至是犯罪。</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="the-power-of-police-officers-to-give-lawful-orders"><a href="https://www.yalelawjournal.org/comment/the-power-of-police-officers-to-give-lawful-orders">The Power of Police Officers to Give “Lawful Orders”</a></h4>
<ul>
<li>作者建立一个道德模型来讨论 什么是警察作出的“合法命令”，以至于公民违反该命令构成犯罪。</li>
<li>在中国语境下，妨碍执行公务的讨论也很多，但主要是聚焦妨碍行为的界定，而几乎没有转向对于公务行为合法性的讨论。相关的讨论可能集中于行政行为无效条件的讨论。但行政行为自始无效这一主张 几乎无法在警察执法以及其他核心行政过程中得到体现。
<h4 id="the-effect-of-judges-gender-on-decisions-regarding-intimate-partner-violence">The effect of judges' gender on decisions regarding intimate-partner violence</h4>
<ul>
<li>性别的影响取决于经验和工作量：当案件数量较多时，经验更丰富的女法官比男法官更有可能批准保护令。</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="法官何时组成合议庭the-company-they-keep-when-and-why-chinese-judges-engage-in-collegiality">【⭐】法官何时组成合议庭The company they keep: When and why Chinese judges engage in collegiality</h4>
<ul>
<li>基于2015年至2017年中国北京一家地方法院判决的23564起案件，我们构建了一个法官合议行为网络，并研究了法官组成合议庭的策略及其潜在影响。我们主张建立外部机制来影响陪审团，并对在脆弱环境中建立联盟的策略进行说明。</li>
<li>对于普通案件，中国法官倾向于与初级法官组成陪审团。在某种程度上，这样的陪审团是他们的舒适区。</li>
<li>在处理复杂案件时，他们倾向于走出自己的舒适区，与更有能力的法官组成合议庭。在这种情况下，他们更倾向于做出艰难的决定，例如在行政诉讼案件中做出不利于政府的裁决，以及在民事案件中反复出现。</li>
<li>这项研究揭示了中国司法政治，并有可能扩大我们对转型社会集体司法决策的理解。</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="prosecuting-corporate-crime-when-firms-are-too-big-to-jail-investigation-deterrence-and-judicial-review"><a href="https://www.yalelawjournal.org/note/prosecuting-corporate-crime-when-firms-are-too-big-to-jail">Prosecuting Corporate Crime when Firms Are Too Big to Jail: Investigation, Deterrence, and Judicial Review</a></h4>
<ul>
<li>摘要：
<ul>
<li>一些公司规模庞大，或具有系统性重要意义，以至于当它们违反法律时，政府无法可信地威胁实施“有效的”刑事制裁。本论文通过将政治经济约束引入公司责任的标准微观经济模型，**展示了“大到无法入狱”（TBTJ）问题如何削弱检察官威慑公司犯罪的能力，即仅对被告公司处以罚款，而不同时起诉负有罪责的个人和强制进行结构性改革。**检察官往往缺乏对负有罪责的个人提出指控或强制实施结构性改革的能力。**本说明进一步说明了仅凭企业刑事责任的风险无法激励TBTJ公司投资内部控制或配合政府调查。**为了遏制TBTJ公司的犯罪行为，检察策略应切实以罚款和非罚款的方式威胁负有罪责的管理人员，而不是过分依赖企业被告的合作。</li>
<li>本说明还从结构上解释了为何在与TBTJ公司协商达成刑事和解时，很少对个人提出起诉：**检察官目前依赖的调查手段可能为公司达成和解提供必要的信息，但无法可靠地提供指控有罪个人所需的证据。**对此，本说明建议让法院成为反对这些结构性因素的堡垒，以防止检察官在没有坚持对潜在的个人罪责进行全面调查的情况下同意大型公司和解。因此，我建议进行立法改革，授权对延期起诉协议进行司法审查，以确保检察官在最终确定公司和解之前收集了足够的证据。</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>美国版的刑事合规问题，但其讨论的困境实际上具有普遍性。罚款在中国意味着调查或者制裁的告一段落，而约谈则更加严重和不确定。中国政府可能拥有更多的规制手段。</li>
<li>但商业巨头、超级平台的刑事责任问题，确实是一个非常值得研究的视角。</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="litigating-data-sovereignty">Litigating Data Sovereignty</h4>
<ul>
<li>化学老师推荐</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="the-original-theory-of-constitutionalism尚未看懂导论">The Original Theory of Constitutionalism【尚未看懂导论】</h4>
<ul>
<li>The sleeping sovereignty 的书评</li>
<li>作者认为原旨主义和活宪法的争论的关键是“谁在统治我？”而忽略一个重要的问题：宪法制定者理解的constitutionalism是什么？他们看待宪法的方式对于今天的我们有什么作用？不仅仅是宪法文本的具体解释之上，而是在宪法秩序的正当性这一意义上。</li>
<li>作者区分了sovereignty 和government，认为美国宪法的困难在于几乎不可能的修改，人民意志几乎不可能被唤醒。</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="davidson-nestor-m-localist-administrative-law-november-10-2016-yale-law-journal-vol-126-no-2-fordham-law-legal-studies-research-paper-no-2867595-available-at-ssrn-httpsssrncomabstract2867595">【⭐】Davidson, Nestor M., Localist Administrative Law (November 10, 2016). Yale Law Journal, Vol. 126, No. 2, Fordham Law Legal Studies Research Paper No. 2867595, Available at SSRN: https://ssrn.com/abstract=2867595</h4>
<ul>
<li>以往的行政法学研究往往集中于联邦层面，无论是对于职业官僚的尊让还是分权原则。而这些基于联邦层面被发展的原则却在基层也得到了适用，尽管基层的情况大不相同。而基层政府的行政往往被系统性地忽视了。</li>
<li>首先，本文详细描述了地方行政，概述了地方机构行动的领域、界定这些机构的政府结构以及地方机构运作的实际细节。</li>
<li>然后，文章从这一经验基础出发，确定了一些特别突出的因素，这些因素可以更透明地指导对各种地方机构行为的司法审查，从法律解释到实质性政策制定，再到执法和许可。这些因素包括<strong>地方政府结构的特殊性和多样性、地方行政中非正式性与程序合法性之间的紧张关系、地方治理中公共领域与私人领域之间错综复杂的相互作用，以及反映地方知识的地方机构专业知识。</strong><br>
最后，这种地方主义视角与地方政府法和行政法领域的核心学术辩论直接相关。对地方行政的理解为地方政府的权力和身份问题增加了一层内在的复杂性，重新调整了关于民主问责制和实验主义的讨论。同样，它也为深化行政法学带来了希望，其视角将覆盖我们纵向联邦制的整个范围。简而言之，地方机构的世界为研究一系列重要但未被充分重视的机构打开了一扇窗。<strong>对这些机构的关注最终将促进地方政府学者对行政法的新讨论，以及行政法学者对治理的更广泛理解。</strong>——how?</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="structural-deregulation">Structural Deregulation</h4>
<ul>
<li>这篇文章描述了一个重要的现象，当总统的行为旨在实现the systematic undermining of an agency’s ability to execute its statutory mandate. 现有的法律规则无法有效地阻止这一点。</li>
<li>作者对比了 structural deregulation 和 substantiv deregulation，后者尽管也可能造成严重的后果，但其相对透明、范围有限，而且容易受到法律的控制。</li>
<li>这篇2021年的文章可能会成为2024年特朗普组建DOGE委员会的预言。</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="cashing-out-a-special-relationship-trends-toward-reconciliation-between-financial-regulation-and-administrative-law">Cashing Out a Special Relationship?: Trends Toward Reconciliation Between Financial Regulation and Administrative Law</h4>
<ul>
<li>金融监管和行政法的关系：表面上二者似乎是同一回事，金融监管的机构和程序形式上受到行政法的约束，但实际上金融监管日常实践并未受到行政法的约束。</li>
<li>一个悖论：这两个领域在基本描述上是协调的，但在日常活动中却隐约分离，在深层逻辑上也不一致。
<ul>
<li>融监管体系似乎与许多其他形式的监管法截然不同：它行动迅速、决策不透明、高度以预防危机为导向--代价是与一般行政程序的某些不一致。</li>
<li>它究竟是行政法一般规则在变革性领域的适用，还是一般规则的例外？</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>美国实践中出现了一种在金融监管领域强化行政法适用的趋势，作者却认为这一做法比较消极：
<ul>
<li>“一刀切 ”框架的冲动忽略了金融监管方法必须而且应该因地制宜的原因。这种常态化趋势将行政工具应用于其设计范围之外的情况，违背了现代金融监管国家的主要原则。其结果是既限制了监管权力的必要行使，又混淆了最尖锐的关注领域。</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="社科研究">社科研究</h1>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[关于本站]]></title>
        <id>https://unlawfulenrichment.github.io/post/about/</id>
        <link href="https://unlawfulenrichment.github.io/post/about/">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-01-25T11:09:48.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>欢迎来到我的小站呀，很高兴遇见你！🤝</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="关于本站">🏠 关于本站</h2>
<p>创建这个blog，实际上的主要目的是为了存放我阅读的文献、案例。因为如果只有自己读，往往会流于潦草。如果有观众，哪怕ta是观念上的存在，可能也会郑重一些。<br>
感谢@四星望月真好吃帮我debug，不然这个网站可能就不会建起来。</p>
<h2 id="博主是谁">👨‍💻 博主是谁</h2>
<p>可以叫我LL</p>
<h2 id="兴趣爱好">⛹ 兴趣爱好</h2>
<p>写字、出去玩、吃、***</p>
<h2 id="联系我呀">📬 联系我呀</h2>
<p>please contact me via Lailucien2628@gmail.com</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello Gridea]]></title>
        <id>https://unlawfulenrichment.github.io/post/hello-gridea/</id>
        <link href="https://unlawfulenrichment.github.io/post/hello-gridea/">
        </link>
        <updated>2018-12-11T16:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>👏  欢迎使用 <strong>Gridea</strong> ！<br>
✍️  <strong>Gridea</strong> 一个静态博客写作客户端。你可以用它来记录你的生活、心情、知识、笔记、创意... ...</p>
]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>👏  欢迎使用 <strong>Gridea</strong> ！<br>
✍️  <strong>Gridea</strong> 一个静态博客写作客户端。你可以用它来记录你的生活、心情、知识、笔记、创意... ...</p>
<!-- more -->
<p><a href="https://github.com/getgridea/gridea">Github</a><br>
<a href="https://gridea.dev/">Gridea 主页</a><br>
<a href="https://fehey.com/">示例网站</a></p>
<h2 id="特性">特性👇</h2>
<p>📝  你可以使用最酷的 <strong>Markdown</strong> 语法，进行快速创作</p>
<p>🌉  你可以给文章配上精美的封面图和在文章任意位置插入图片</p>
<p>🏷️  你可以对文章进行标签分组</p>
<p>📋  你可以自定义菜单，甚至可以创建外部链接菜单</p>
<p>💻  你可以在 <strong>Windows</strong>，<strong>MacOS</strong> 或 <strong>Linux</strong> 设备上使用此客户端</p>
<p>🌎  你可以使用 <strong>𝖦𝗂𝗍𝗁𝗎𝖻 𝖯𝖺𝗀𝖾𝗌</strong> 或 <strong>Coding Pages</strong> 向世界展示，未来将支持更多平台</p>
<p>💬  你可以进行简单的配置，接入 <a href="https://github.com/gitalk/gitalk">Gitalk</a> 或 <a href="https://github.com/SukkaW/DisqusJS">DisqusJS</a> 评论系统</p>
<p>🇬🇧  你可以使用<strong>中文简体</strong>或<strong>英语</strong></p>
<p>🌁  你可以任意使用应用内默认主题或任意第三方主题，强大的主题自定义能力</p>
<p>🖥  你可以自定义源文件夹，利用 OneDrive、百度网盘、iCloud、Dropbox 等进行多设备同步</p>
<p>🌱 当然 <strong>Gridea</strong> 还很年轻，有很多不足，但请相信，它会不停向前 🏃</p>
<p>未来，它一定会成为你离不开的伙伴</p>
<p>尽情发挥你的才华吧！</p>
<p>😘 Enjoy~</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
</feed>